um yeah I wanted to get your thoughts on
a on a on a specific kind of angle to
some of the computational stuff that
we've been doing lately sure it's always
um I don't I I I I I knew that um you
would have something on your mind uh but
I I was busy racking my brains trying to
um think what is it that we're going to
be talking about and then I thought well
it doesn't matter with you it's always
interesting so I'll just see what it is
and then we'll we'll take it from there
so so what is it that's on your mind all
right uh thanks um so so here's what I
have um we have a um we have a pre-print
and this is um Adam Goldstein and um uh
attaining uh Jang a student of mine and
I um have a a preprint on the following
what what I wanted to do was to uh
address this issue of uh nonobvious um
cognitive properties in very simple
systems okay and you know I I like this
kind of stuff and so and so the thing
that I chose specifically specifically
was uh sorting algorithms so these are
very simple algorithms that computer
scientists of you know all CS students
study these and so I'll just give you a
very quick uh rundown of of what we had
found and so and so they they're a good
model system because they're fully
deterministic so there's they're they're
completely um transparent at six lines
of code or so so there's nowhere to hide
you know in biology there's always yet
more mechanism that could be involved
but here you see every all the steps of
the algorithm um fully deterministic
very very simple everybody knows
everybody thinks they know what they're
capable of everybody's been studying
them it's it's very obvious and so so I
thought okay let's um let's see let's
see if we can find any any surprises
there and and we made a couple of uh
tweaks to be able to study them from
this basil cognition perspective and
then I think there may be sort of a
psychoanalytic perspective here that I
want to um that I want to probe probe
with with your opinions on so the first
thing we did is we just visualized um so
so the way they work is you start with a
string of integers let's say 100
integers they're jumbled up in random
order and what the algorithms are going
to do is eventually sort them into order
so that it's monotonic from you know
from from one to 100 and so what you can
do is you can visualize the progression
of Any Given string in that space it
starts off somewhere over here where the
r where there it's quite random and then
they all sort of move to a spot where in
fact guaranteed to move to a spot where
everybody's in the same order so so what
you can do is you can plot this notion
of sorted you know how how well sorted a
given string is and you see that over
time it's sort of it it increases so
okay so that's so that's the journey
through space that this thing is taking
that's the space it lives in and now we
can we can ask a couple of interesting
questions uh the first question that we
asked was uh in the in in James's sense
of um delayed gratification in other
words if we put a barrier in its place
is it capable of moving backwards away
from its goal in order to reap gains
later on you know the business with the
two magnets separated by a piece of wood
versus Romeo and Juliet separated and so
on so um keep in mind that in these
algorithms there is nothing like that
there is nothing explicitly in the
algorithm about well you know if you
come upon a barrier then you should
temporarily back off there's nothing
like that we kept the algorithms exactly
as they are the way we do a barrier is
we simulate a broken cell so every cell
has a certain number and the algorithm
says move the four and the five and you
know but what happens if one of them is
broken they won't move if they won't
move and this this this breaks an
assumption in these algorithms usually
you assume that the that the that the
hardware is reliable if the algorithm
says swap the numbers they swap and in
fact the algorithm doesn't have any
logic built in to see wait did it swap
or didn't it it doesn't have any of that
it assumes it just goes on its merry way
assuming that what it said actually took
place we said well biology isn't like
that you have um the biological medium
is is notoriously unreliable and noisy
but specifically if we put a barrier
you're going along and you're sorting
all of a sudden you come you you need to
move this number to get to to to improve
things but it won't move it's broken and
there one of two ways it could be broken
either um it could uh uh you know refuse
to be moved at all or it could refuse to
um uh to to to to request to be move
we'll deal with that momentarily but but
anyway let's say it's broken and so what
we found is that
um these these algorithms uh despite the
fact of not having any specific code for
it when they do come to a to a barrier
like this they back off meaning the
sordidness actually drops the string
becomes less sorted they do some other
stuff they move other numbers around and
then eventually they go around and
things and things improve and so this so
they have some ability for this kind of
delayed gratification they they can back
away from their goal uh in order to reap
gains later on and they have a little
Horizon that they're willing to uh you
know they're willing and able to to to
do that so that was that was kind of the
first the first thing we found and
that's not really the thing I want to
focus on but I thought I would exp you
know say it just in case you had
anything interesting to say about that
so so there's this there's this
interesting new can I pause you for a
moment um sorry you know the the I just
want to be sure I'm following correctly
Mike so this um algorithm uh is it a
stepwise procedure or is it an end goal
that it's um in other words is it aiming
for the end goal the totally sorted um
sequence or is it just following the
steps that that are coded it's the steps
there is no it is not a um it is not an
explicit goal directed loop at all
basically uh it it has certain criteria
it says look at some numbers and then
based on that shuffle the numbers and
and that's it now which just so happens
that if you execute that long enough you
will eventually end up with a string but
there is no logic in there there is no
logic that asks uh is is you know how
are we doing did it work how are we
doing is it sorted there isn't any of
that there's no self-monitoring there's
no there's nothing like that yeah okay
thank you so okay um the second thing we
did is uh instead so so the usual these
the way these algorithms are are usually
done is that there's a centralized
controller that's uh sort of can see
Godlike can see the whole string and is
following the algorithm and is moving
you know moving numbers around so what
we did was was we got rid of that and we
said instead each cell each individual
cell is following it the algorithm so
the four wants a five on its on its
right and the three on its left and and
each each individual cell has
preferences about what its neighbors are
but there is no single Central
controller that sees the whole thing and
if you do that um it still works um and
it's you know it's fine it still it
still works so that's interesting you
can make it sort of bottom up and
distribute it in that in that way but
that also allows you to do an
interesting thing which you couldn't do
before which is you can make a chimeric
string you can make a string compos an
array of numbers composed of numbers
that are actually following different
algorithms so so we looked at three
different or three different sorting
algorithms that we uh that we uh used
selection sort insertion sort and bubble
sort they're called so normally you have
one algorithm and you're following that
at one algorithm to move the numbers
around but now that the numbers are
moving themselves around what you can
say is well some number of them are
going to be following this policy some
numbers some some of them are going to
be following that policy and uh and if
you do that it also still works meaning
that they don't all have to be following
the same policy but here's the here's
the crazy part imagine you have a you
have a an an array of of 100 cells and
each of those cells has a number to it
that's what you're sorting you're
sorting on that number and they're
starting out randomly what what we did
was to to assign uh algorithms to each
of those cells randomly one of two so so
um Adam came up with a nice name for it
he calls it an algot type the way you
have a genotype and a phenotype now now
every cell has an algot type the algot
type is either it's either the it's
either bubble swort or it's insertion
sort that's it and the alot types are
also selected
randomly now we ask a simple question
during the lifetime of this this array
as it's doing its sorting
thing what are what's the internal
structure like that is what is the
probability that any given cell looks to
its neighbor and says oh he's just like
me same algot type as me what's the
probability of that now in the beginning
that probability is 50% because we
assign algot types to numbers randomly
so you know that it's a random it's a
50-50 whether the guy next to you is
same as you
at the end of this thing it's also
random because at the end we're sorting
on digits on the digit values and we
know that the assignment of Digit values
to algot types Is Random so at the end
it's also going to be random but now the
question is what does it do in the
middle and what we find that it does in
the middle is if if this is um this is
time here and this is you know 50% it's
here uh it starts out at 50% it goes up
and then it then comes back down in
other words what happens during the
Sorting is that
cells tend to Cluster next to ones like
them they tend to Cluster next to their
own kin basically now keep in mind in
the algorithm there is nothing about
there is no code in the algorithm what
algo type am I what algot type is my
neighbor I want to go sit next to this
one I don't like sitting next to that
one there's nothing like that in there
if you examine the the physics of the
system determined by the by the
algorithm itself you don't see any of
that the only time you see this is if
you actually uh is is if we actually
look and uh and and and and and ask this
question of uh we know what their algot
types are and we say so so in a certain
sense so you can probably see why I
started thinking uh you know about
analysis because it's what we are doing
is uncovering a hidden cause of their
behavior that is to them not Apparent at
all we can see that oh you're clustering
in a particular way there's a behavioral
pattern that we're
identifying here but it isn't explicitly
coded by anything that you know if they
were to examine their own code or if
anybody would examine the wrong code
there's nothing in the code that says
that so there's so so there are a few
interesting things here that I that I
really like one is that it's a kind of
uh it's an extremely minimal metaphor
for this existential um uh condition of
living things where eventually in this
universe the inexorable force of the
algorithm is going to pull apart all of
those uh um you know clustered pieces
because in the end everybody's got to
get sorted according to their number So
eventually the physics grinds you down
and and sort of you know un undoes
whatever organization you had at the
beginning but during the process you
have some amount of time where in a way
consistent with the physics I mean
there's no magic you're following the
algorithm but there's an interesting
behavioral
um tendency is is you know that that
that you're able to satisfy for some
period of time during during your
lifetime and it's something that
simultaneously is it's it's not against
the algorithm that um that uh that
you're that you're following it's
consistent with it but it's also but
it's not specified in the algorithm and
for some amount of time it's actually at
Cross purposes because because you're
being you know your your behavior you're
you're you're keeping things together
that eventually are going to need to be
pulled apart we also did one more
experiment we
asked how strong is this tendency to be
to be uh to to keep together because and
and one way one way you can um one way
you can ask that is by allowing repeat
digits if I allow repeat digits you know
let's say let's say let's say there's um
we we have 100 total and every and every
digit can occur 10 times so there's only
10 digits total you know there's 10
fives 10 sixes and so on if you do that
what happens is then you can kind of
satisfy both in other words in a run of
10 fives they can be where they're
supposed to be but five of them could be
one algot type and five of them could be
the other so it sort of makes it
possible for you to retain the
clustering while still be consistent
with the algorithm and if you do that
they cluster even more you know which
which shows that these things are
actually somewhat across purposes if you
take off the pressure if you allow them
to do what they really want to do which
is to be clustered the clustering goes
up um yeah so so I'm interested in this
in in your thoughts on just in general
this notion of of a system uh this is an
extremely simple one but of course you
know you and I are both interested in
minimal agents and and so on um these
kinds of explicit drives and behaviors
that aren't in the algorithm that are
emergent that are not obvious but that
can be discovered if we take seriously
you know uh the study of how this thing
reacts in this in the problem space that
it's working and if we don't assume for
the moment that it's just even though
it's deterministic and and so on that we
don't assume that it's this dumb thing
that only does what the what the
algorithm says um it really you know it
really it really made me feel like um
yeah we were we were uncovering these
hidden hidden motivations for the
patterns and Its Behavior that well it's
not complex enough to of course realize
it but but we can see them so yeah I
don't know what do you what do you think
about all
that um well first of all as always you
know you I I I don't know um how you
come up with the problems uh that that
you spend your time on you know they you
you have the most extraordinarily
creative mind um you know so I just as
as you tell the story I'm thinking this
is Mike Len
you nobody else is going to have this
conversation with you
ever um are we getting some sort of
interference no I'm trying to shut off
somebody's texting me and I'm trying to
okay shut it off yeah um so I was
thinking it through and trying to
understand why um it would do what it's
doing and obviously I don't know the
algorithms but it it was sort of making
sense to me that why these emergent
behaviors I was thinking there ways in
which I can understand this would happen
uh for example um your own algo type is
probably more predictable uh if it's
functioning by the same principle that
you are you will you will prefer to
operate in a space that is that is
understandable to that behaves in the
way that you expect and there's less
work required from you so so you know
the how that comes about um made made a
sort of you know putative sense to me uh
then when you ask the question um with
then you know what what you were
describing was of course emergent
properties of the system as as you later
labeled it yourself um but then you
asked this very interesting question
about when you say you're linking it
to you're saying to psychoanalysis but
really uh it's it's broader than
psychoanalysis it's a A system that has
explicit and
implicit um
principles um and so it's really the the
the model I would use is is a a general
sort of multi multiple memory systems
sort of model and um where there are non
declarative and declarative U
modules and um then I was thinking uh in
that the it works in the reverse uh of
what you've described in the sense that
what is non declarative uh is
um the is the more
um bottom up it's the more it's the more
um sort of
predetermined uh and what is declarative
what is explicit uh is the more emergent
you know what what couldn't be um
predicted and and needs to be dealt with
on the Fly is what is explicit so it's
an interesting uh I mean the fact that
you drew that analogy which I have to
say I wouldn't even have thought of
again you know this is why I'm saying
this is Mike Len you have to remember
that you're Mark SS and that's Mike Len
and now you got to start thinking
differently um but since you made that
connection which I wouldn't have made I
find it interesting that for me it would
what what I would what I would call the
emergent part um is the part that's
explicit um and so explicit in the
cognitive sense as opposed to expit in
the coding sense um you know in other
words this was explicitly coded but this
this Behavior emerges um what I think is
explicitly coded uh in our multiple
memory systems um is is what is non
declarative and uh what is what what is
implicit and emergent is what is
declarative because that's where the
uncertainty is that's where the
unpredict ability is which links with my
way of thinking about Consciousness
which is that it has it's it's felt
uncertainty
it's now why do I think uh that the
nondeclarative
systems um are um the are equivalent to
your explicit coding um I think it's as
I'm trying to unpack my own intuition
why do I have that intuition um well
first of all I could link to what I've
just said uh in that which is a kind of
functionalist account uh in that um
the what is implicit is what is more
certain uh in the memory sense of the
word in other words let me use the word
n declarative so then it's clearer that
I'm talking about memory systems so the
N declarative systems um are non
declarative because one has a high
confidence in those beliefs uh that that
um they're not subject to review uh this
is always the same so so in terms of a
hierarchical predictive model uh you're
talking about the layers in the
hierarchy uh which are which which are
simpler and um and more
generalizable um the way I think of a
predictive hierarchy by the way I don't
normally picture it as a pyramid I
picture it as a concentric onion uh and
I think of the core of the onion as the
the Deep layers uh of the predictive
model and and that's where there's the
greatest confidence uh and so the
simplest most generalizable predictions
are at the core uh and as you move to
the periphery so you're dealing with
with um eventualities on the fly so one
of the reasons why I think of the non
declarative systems um as as the um
explicit in the sense of pre-programmed
is because they are they are more
um there's more there's more
predetermination higher confidence more
generalizability um and and a simpler um
algorithm is being followed down there
um and of course the converse applies to
the periphery um the another way another
reason that I think that way is because
I think that the non declarative memory
systems are the ones that function most
like reflexes and instincts um which are
um which are the pre-programmed
predictions you know you these are the
predictions that are determined by
natural selection uh that that and and
the as we
automatize um our acquired predictions
so they function more like reflexes and
instincts they they they are more
they're more automatized they're more
unconscious they're more um predictable
they are simpler they're more
generalizable uh and the periphery of
the predictive model is specialized for
complexity for context
sensitivity um and uh so that's where
the uncertainty is um it's it's also in
other words it's what is more required
it is what is more um unique to to to to
to me here and now as opposed to what is
generally true of all versions of of of
my type uh things that always function
that way so um so the meaning of the
word explicit and implicit uh in memory
systems terms um is the opposite of the
meaning of the terms uh in the way that
we are using them in your in your
emerging properties of your of your um
of your
system um so those are my uh initial
thoughts um but it links to an issue
that is is is extremely um interesting
and I think cuts to the heart of of the
whole problem of Consciousness which is
you know what do we mean by explicit why
why does anything become explicit in the
sense that the system now has to monitor
its own States um I I think that is the
so so I'm as you know I'm working on an
artificial Consciousness project myself
um and in our the the the the
computational architecture that that
we're um designing and adjusting as as
we go along this is this has become this
is one of the problems we're busy
tackling right now um is is um we can
make the the this our our agent function
perfectly well without there being any
obvious sort of distinction between what
is explicit and what is implicit and we
have to kind of introduce that uh in
order to try and get some what we're
calling biological plausibility but it
actually has two different meanings the
one is to get it to function like I
expect it has to you know and that's not
biological plausibility it's Mark S's
plausibility and the other is to make it
function more like a you know vertebrate
brain what what we know about how uh
well actually more mamalian brains is
what I'm using as my as my sort of
starting point but um in in other words
a brain with cortex um and um so we we
we're having to introduce a constraint
uh you know on the way that it works in
order to try to make this distinction
between what is explicit and what is
implicit which is of course very bad way
of going about doing things because and
then I realized that as we were doing
that that um it's it's due to a concrete
way of thinking you know of course there
can be this functional distinction in
the system doesn't have to actually
coincide with its architecture in other
words the architect you mustn't map the
architecture onto your Concepts the your
the concepts of what functions it's
performing like what you're talking
about but now these emergent properties
they're not in any of the code you know
that they're not any in any of the of
the modules in your flow diagram but
nevertheless they emerge they exist
these distinctions exist um without them
being coded for and without them
coinciding with the with the with the
brute structure of the of the algorithm
or or the or the or or or the uh you
know the structure of the of the the the
program
um but that issue of the meaning of
explicit in the Consciousness sense of
the word um it's it's the issue you know
why does anything have to become
explicit what what does explicitness do
um and
um it has I think to do with when a
system uh is uncertain about its own
state
um and therefore has to focus on
monitoring of its own
States but nevertheless we come back to
the problem uh that I started with in my
response to you um which is that um it
is the opposite meaning of the of the of
of the of the the terms end up having
diametrically opposite meaning the
meaning of explicit and implicit in the
phenomenological sense uh as opposed to
uh in in the in the um function
functional architecture sense of you
know what is explicitly coded and what
emerges
um those are my thoughts about that
problem does does that um resonate with
you or lead you to any interesting
places yeah super interesting I hadn't
realized uh I hadn't realized about the
inversion I think that's that's
incredibly important and um I wonder if
I wonder if tracking down when so so we
can sort of look at the kinds of systems
that that we're working in as like one
end of the spectrum the very minimal
kind and then over here is you know the
sort of thing the Mamon brain you're
trying to model one wonders whether that
inversion takes place somewhere along
that Spectrum right and whether that's a
that's some sort of face transition or
whether it's a gradual Flip or I I don't
know yet because I just you know I'm
just taking this on now but um but yeah
the fact that it's backwards
uh I wonder if that is actually an
important Criterion for some of the
things that we are interested in you
know to distinguish TR truly simple
models that don't have whatever
properties from okay now you're into
something that's a true agent what you
know maybe maybe that flip is is is
important to that um and so that's the F
that's the first thing so I need to
think I need to think harder about this
this this inverted mapping and then the
other thing is that you know this this
question which we wrestle with all the
time in our models is like yeah what
what do you bake in to make it do do
whatever it's supposed to do I mean in
in our example what keeps what keeps
striking me is that the thing that we've
observed and who knows what else right
so I'm sure there's other things to
observe we're just not smart enough to
test for them yet you know this
clustering was just something that that
we thought of to do but I'm sure there's
other things to do um it it doesn't have
any real like we didn't have to do
anything for that to emerge mean meaning
it isn't it isn't any there's nothing in
the algorithm that remotely is about
optimizing that so to some to so to some
extent this
apparent uh you know the the apparent
tendency of the system to optimize a
particular behavior is completely
emerging we didn't have to do anything
and so so one wonders you know as we
think about okay how do we construct
things like that maybe a lot of it we
don't construct maybe it it's Emer I
don't know where it comes from right but
but maybe it really emerges under
extremely minimal conditions and that it
makes me think that if something is as
dumb as a as a you know six-line sorting
algorithm can have these unexpected
behavioral tendencies that have to be
discovered by experiment that we cannot
you know predict in advance the more
complicated things we make you know who
knows what they're doing right it's like
that that's I mean that's part of why
why I started this is because I wanted
to have an extremely simple system yeah
you know and it seems like already there
you have this kind of and I I mean the
thing you started with I mean it's it's
amazing because it took me uh probably
probably a couple of months to to to
realize what you said you know right off
the bat at the beginning which is that
what it looks like they're doing is
they're minimizing uncertainty about
their neighbors right because having a
neighbor who's like you means yeah so so
I eventually got there too but that took
me that took me a couple of months to to
realize and actually Carl and I um
talked about it uh a few weeks ago the
thing about that and I think that's a
perfectly reasonable explanation the
thing about it is that there is nothing
in the algorithm about that there's
nothing about making predictions testing
you know we're doing some we actually
doing some experiments right now to see
like how many interactions they have
before they cluster do they actually
have to spend some time with each other
before they realize that hey this is
this you know this one's just like me so
but but but all of that is completely
emergent so I just you know this thing
if it wasn't all already fundamental
enough this this this surprise
minimization principle it it seems now
even more you know just baked in you
don't need to do much of anything you
all you get that you know just from from
extremely minimal systems
yeah um so I don't know if if there's a
literature on this suddenly what you
just said um made me realize that this
principle um of preferring to be uh in
the um neighborhood of agents that
function like me because they are more
predictable um they reduce my
uncertainty um it it it it makes me
realize with a sort of chill down my
spine that this is obviously part of um
of of of of prejudice you know why why
people want to be with their own kind
you know is that they're more
predictable you you you you know what's
going on you know what to do you know
what to expect and being with others in
in the social sense uh it makes you um
uncertain uh and and therefore um
increases your free energy and therefore
you don't want to be there it's I say it
sends a chill down my spine because it
makes makes me realize how you know uh
how how little Prospect one has of being
able to engineer um socially engineer
this out of us the only the only way to
do it is to make sure we all have a
common
enemy so but that's a sort of a side
thought as I say I don't know if anybody
is has has said that um maybe that's
generally recognized to be the case but
it for me it's a I've only discovered
that in my own mind right now in this
conversation yeah yeah I mean it's it's
amazing that uh something like that is
is present at the very bottom of you
know it didn't take much it didn't take
any any Evolution at all in fact to come
upon this right but it it actually this
idea actually cropped up um about a
month ago um some colleagues and I um
were discussing uh you know Ai and
diverse like diverse intelligence and
all that and uh what we had a lot of
debates about um this sort of spectrum
you can imagine the sort of spectrum
where on one end it's things like um
objectophilia right where you you sort
of completely mistake the the amount of
AG agency and whatever system you're
dealing with and you fall in love with a
bridge or an Eiffel Tower or something
you know people do of course um which
which are you know sort of not at the
level that that you think they are but
the and so and so that's that's one type
of error but but the other type of error
is exactly what you just said which
basically you know if you're if you're
too strict about saying well I I don't
believe you know you're you you don't
have the um the origin story or
composition that I do and therefore I
don't think you have a real mind I think
you're you know faking it as as what
they say about certain I mean the the
the far end of that is something like
only love your own kind right that's the
that's that's what you were just saying
you know that so so we want it so so we
spent a lot of time talking
about how we could arrive at principal
strategies for picking criteria along
that because you don't want to be at
either one of these you know either one
of these polls you want to um match sort
of impedance match the the kind of
relationship you have with a system to
what and and and I firmly believe that
even in the absence of you know aliens
and whatnot um we're going to be
surrounded by really radically different
systems we're gonna have to like work on
getting this right so I you know from
that perspective yeah I I completely
agree with you that that this this this
this is an important thing to uh to get
right and I think our fundamental you
know that surprise minimization but I
wonder you know I wonder if one thing
you can do to alter how this works is to
sort of re reframe what it is that
you're measuring let's assume let's
assume for a minute that that yes you
don't want surprises you want you want
to uh you know you want you want it
predictable but now the question is what
about and so if we can get away from
superficial um kinds of differences that
drive you know social you know distress
and stuff like that and focus on
fundamental things then then maybe this
can actually make sense so so you know
what I would like to be surrounded by is
what you know humans with the same DNA n
that's not what I'm measuring maybe we
measure something else maybe we measure
um kindness or pro- adaptive you know
pro-social behaviors or um somebody who
has the same kind of existential
concerns that I do or something like
that right so so so shift the
measurables in a way that it's actually
you know it's actually better I don't
know that's that's that's that's where
I've been trying to and trying to think
about how to create principal uh
strategies for
that um so
think you
just put it it is very much um a concern
of mine as I'm working on this
artificial
Consciousness uh the Prejudice uh of
it's not like me therefore it can't have
um this valuable thing that I've got
um I'm I'm very exercised by I mean in
my field I have it even with with uh
colleagues who won't acknowledge
Consciousness in creatures which are too
far from us um in in in in terms of
their phenotype um let alone you know
artificial um agents the the Prejudice
is just enormous and so it's interesting
to link that with what we've just been
talking about again I hadn't thought of
that um the the solution that
we um mammals at least um have come to
that functions in the other direction um
is an an
epistemophilic um uh inclination you
know that it's that it's important to um
to approach what is
uncertain a positive a positive
attraction to to to to gaining more
knowledge um and therefore to engaging
with what is novel with what is not
understood with what is with what is
it's what becomes interesting you know
so so there's a the misoc cortical misol
liic dopamine system functions like that
in the mamalian brain it's it's its
homeostatic set point is to be in a
state of uncertainty it's it's it's it's
it's a in in homeostatic deviation uh if
it's bored you know if if if
everything's predictable then that need
is not being met the need to to engage
with novelty it's a sort of what makes
us forage um it's what makes us
explored it's what makes people like you
and me exist at all you that we we're
constantly attracted to what is to what
is not known um and you can see uh over
longer time scales uh the biological
advantage of that because to engage with
uncertainty is in the long long term to
reduce uncertainty um so you know the
world's not going to bite you in the
butt in future because you you you you
engaged with it uh it now
proactively um but then an entirely
different line of thought that was
triggered in me as I was listening to
what what you were saying um is that
really what you're talking about is a
sort of swarm intelligence isn't it uh
where where each creature has a very uh
um
limited range of behaviors and then
although each one of them is doing this
very limited thing um it it it what
emerges is is very complex behaviors by
the by the Swarm as a whole um none of
so there's no master program u in each
um uh member of the Swarm but the Swarm
as a whole produces this this um much
more intricate um outcome that maps onto
what you were talking about in terms of
your algorithm uh and the interesting
emergent behaviors that that that you
described to me but then I realized that
this links actually to one of your basic
concerns which is that we multicellular
creatures are all of us actually swarms
of cells and um so this is uh but but we
are not we are not um swarms of equal
cells um we we have um we have nerve
cells and and uh and bone cells and and
so on um which are specialized for in
some respects of course they are all of
them just you know animal cells but uh
in in another sense they they're not
they so you do end up having sort of um
m controllers in the in in in the nerve
cells for example in relation to to to
to other cells it's so there's a it's
it's not we are not just a swarm you
know we are we're we're some there's
interesting ways in which you can
understand the cooperation between all
of our individual cells in the um on the
model on the analogy of a swarm but
there other ways in which that analogy
breaks down then the other thought that
was marked in Me by by what you were
just saying um is um at what point does
one is one justified in speaking of
cognition I mean what is it that what
does the term cognition refer to really
um if a if a you have a very simple
algorithm that always does exactly the
same thing
um where none of this kind of emergent
behavior of the kind you've just
described happens uh is that cognition
of a very very very basil kind uh or
does one only uh have a reason to speak
of cognition once emergent behaviors
once once there are novel problems um or
at least novel phenomena uh novel comput
computations which are not to go back to
the very beginning of our conversation
which are not um written into the code
you know computations which which are
implicit in the sense that we were using
which are emergent in the sense that we
were using those two terms um does that
qualify as cognition um and if it does
bearing in mind um my own
um um beliefs about what constitutes
Consciousness and you you and I have
spoken about this many times before
functionally what constitutes a
conscious what is probably definitional
functionally of a conscious agent is an
agent which can solve novel problems um
it it has to have some way um of feeling
its way through the problem in other
words of monitoring is this going well
or is this going badly because it's not
written into my into my DNA as it were
you know it's it's this is something
that I've never um that that I have no
predictions for I now have to I now have
to predict the present uh and and and
how do you do that well you have to
palpate how well or badly is this going
and then you have to change your mind um
that's
my I mean putting it in very simple
simplified terms that's my Criterion for
what what is U what is um
plausibly potentially a conscious uh
agent but but now I realize in saying
that that then there's no distinction um
between what qualifies as a as as
something called cognition and and what
qualifies as something called
Consciousness um the only way I could um
find a
um a justification for continuing to use
those words differently is that there
are um operations which become
automatized uh which were once not there
so in other words something Rises to the
level of of um explicit in the in the
psychological sense of word one as of
feeling your way through the problem
then you learn from the experience and
you lay down new predictions which can
become uh very confident and automatized
predictions so they're the products of
Consciousness but they are not in the
present functioning consciously so those
I think it's it it it it makes sense to
me that you would have to call those
cognitive operations because they're the
products of learning um but the actual
work of of learning learning the actual
learning from experience with the
emphasis on the word experience you know
um that part is conscious cognition uh
it's working memory as opposed to
long-term memory which is which is now I
laid down a prediction on the basis of
the predictive work um that that that
that I that I
did but but let me ask you that question
that I began with and what would your
definition of of cognition be uh in the
sense that you're looking for um basil
cognition what what constitutes
cognition as opposed to wrote um
following a
program yeah so so I agree with you I
think it's fundamentally about problem
solving and feeling your way through a
problem and specifically in um in
vulnerable creatures because uh it's
different if if if you are a composite
being that uh is in danger of falling
apart into your component pieces it
becomes a whole other business you know
feeling it way through problems has a
has a whole other business to it um and
I think that's that's that's what we
mean by cognition and I'm willing to as
you know I'm willing to take it very
basily and I don't think it has to be
the complex metacognitive stuff that
that that we have um but what I'm
realizing now uh is that I'm not
sure if if there are any you know when
so so so we we my initial um intuition
was like yours that there would be very
you know there would be rote kinds of
things and then there would be these
like more complex emerging things I'm
not sure there are any of the first part
anymore and and the reason I say that is
because if if you were to look at these
um algorithms how much more rote can you
get they are fully deterministic there's
not even a pseudo random number call
there they are completely deterministic
they are completely transparent you
they're very simple there are there is
no more hidden mechanism of biology to
look at same thing with our Gene
regulatory networks that we showed could
have six different kinds of learning
just again just couple differential
equations so so I if from something as
dumb and simple as this we can already
see the ability to solve new problems
meaning go around the barriers and right
and we can already see that they are
optimizing things that are nowhere
explicitly provided a mechanism for like
like um minimizing distinction from from
your neighbor I mean I I don't know that
that there are any that don't have that
I mean maybe maybe we could try to come
up with some but it makes me you know
even if we were to come up with
something extremely dumb
um I I I don't know that our failure to
find these kind of properties is uh
anything but a lack of imagination on
our part you know like like I'm you know
we could come up with some sort of bit
adder or something that just adds bits
and we'd say Okay surely this thing
doesn't do anything else other than this
we can c and maybe but but but having
seen this in sorting algorithms that
distance has gotten really thin and now
I'm starting to wonder if our inability
to to observe it in simple things is
just lack of imagination and our you
know evolutionary training on very
complicated things where we're just you
know we're not good at seeing so I don't
know um you know and and of course it
leads me to this kind of um you know
sort of a more pist view where uh the
these kind of properties to me look like
they're baked in at at the very
beginning you know maybe wherever
mathematics comes from I don't know but
but but but baked in very early on and
then and then the other thing I think I
feel strongly about is that we have to
do experiments so we cannot just
observationally look at something and
say well I can see it this thing is dumb
it's not going to do anything I I don't
I think we're not good at that at all
I'm not I don't think it's possible
anyway but I think we're we're just bad
at it and uh we need to do experiments
we need to do barriers we need to try
various kinds of training techniques we
need to see what is this thing doing
when when we give it a little leeway you
know um yeah what what what what does it
look like from its perspective and you
you said you also said something very
very interesting about like yeah you can
you can treat this thing as a
distributed agent from the sales point
of view and from the sales point of view
okay who are my neighbors and all of
that but uh somebody in it might have
been Carl or it might have been Adam but
but somebody was saying the other day
when we were talking about this look at
it from the Clusters point of view
because in forming these clusters maybe
we do have a temporary high level higher
level of organization there's a you know
there's a and and and sure you know it's
Dynamic meaning Pieces come and go but
so are we we we're we're a molecular
ship of thesias in the cellular one
right so we we come and go to and uh
maybe there's another story to tell from
the perspective of each cluster as to
what the world looks like so that's you
know that's that's where I've been
recently is is is really thinking about
how to how to see the world from the
perspective of these weird agents you
know and what what does it look like
what what is it like to be I so I so I
don't think it's a crazy question to ask
what's it like to to
be a a chunk of data being sorted I
don't you know what's it like to be the
Sorting algorithm what's it like I I'm
sort of now open to that that gets back
to your you know the Consciousness
question you know like I'm I there may
be inner perspectives like valuable
inner perspectives in all of these
things I don't know yeah I um since our
very first conversations uh I I've told
you that um you you you've made me um
much more radical than I when already I
was in trouble uh in relation to my
colleagues um in in in reducing
everything to you know what the
vertebrate brain stem is capable of um
but um you know you've you've persuaded
me that it goes way way way lower than
that um in terms of what is um plausibly
a cognitive and and plausibly a
conscious system um I I also always end
up finding that
um there can't be a sharp dividing line
at which point it becomes you know so
there has to be uh gradation one has to
speak of protoconsciousness or Proto
cognition and you know and um the that
that has to go all the way down you know
so the the I I'm with you there it's not
entirely the same as pan psychism but
you know it's it's it's it's it's
difficult to say in which way it's not
pan psychism but now let me in trying to
in trying to um to not be a pan psychist
let let me take it a step further uh and
it goes back to what we were saying a
few minutes ago in this conversation
when when when I was saying in one
respect we um composite creatures are
just a swarm a swarm of cells uh and
each cell is just doing its you know
it's from the cell's point of view it's
just this is this is what I do that's
what I always do there's no cognition
going on here I do I do I always do
exactly the same thing um and then you
could say well from the cluster point of
view so the where the emerging behaviors
arise or from the swarm's point of view
what Adam or or Carl had said to you you
know well what what is it like from the
point of view of being the Swarm or what
is it like from the point of view of
being the cluster um that that um is one
way of going but another way of going is
back to the point I made um in when I
said there's ways in which we are not a
sworn in that we we do have Master cells
um and and slave cells and they they're
they're they're they're not on all fours
they're not all doing the same thing
once you start to have um cells within
this cluster or cells within the Swarm
um that are monitoring um at a higher
level uh than the than the um soldiers
I'm thinking of of ants now um you know
once you have generals and soldiers um
then you maybe maybe you you then you
know can more justifiably speak of the
mental processes being at the level of
the of the organizing overseeing um
overarching cells than than not not
every cell then has equal dignity in
terms of its
cognitiv that that that gives me a
really interesting idea that we should
try experimentally in our system which
is I can make some of the we can make
some of the cells more powerful than
others we can let them see a little bit
further or we can let them push a little
harder in terms of where they want to go
and see what effect that has if we right
right now everybody's equal but but I
see your point I think it's very
interesting um if there if there are
regionalizations like that I wonder if
we will see some sort of substructure
within the I'm sort of visualizing a
nervous system within the cluster right
so you have a cluster and and and there
are there's a pattern of of the of the
more powerful cells within you know sort
of organizing like makeing this up I
don't know if this will happen or not
but but I can sort of Imagine right a
temporary almost nervous system I think
we we'll do that I'll I'll I'll talk
very it makes my mind suddenly leap back
to your worms um and I remember that uh
there was um I forget exactly the
anatomy that you told me about but there
was something about um the the uh
something like the epithelial cells had
functionality uh that the that the
intestinal cells didn't have I forget as
I say what the anatomy was but you you
could you could grow a new worm from
some cells and you could not grow a new
worm from other cells well this is yeah
the worms so the worms um they have a a
population of adult stem cells and uh if
you cut a piece that has even one of
these stem cells in it you will get you
know you can get a whole worm if you cut
a piece and there are regions of the
animal where you can cut off like the
tip of the nose has no stem cells in it
if you cut off that tip of the nose it
will not you know it it won't but but I
think it's um I think it's uh a matter
of the hardware and not the information
because uh so so these these stem cells
are the source of new cell types they
produce the stuff you need to make a
proper worm right but I don't think they
carry much of the information because
we've done another experiment and this
is not published yet but but we've we
know what the answer is when you when
you take a little piece out of a
two-headed worm and you irradiate it
like crazy to kill all of the stem cells
that are in it and you take just those
sematic cells and you shove it into the
body of a one-headed worm under some
percentage of the time what ends up
happening is that that one headed worm
now becomes converted to be two-headed
so that information did not require the
stem cells it did not require new cell
types the the transplant in fact will
all die they you know the those cells
only live 30 days or so um but the
information lives on and so so I think
there's a real distinction here about
what you need to know what to do versus
what do you need to actually build you
know the body of the worm